<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mirrour of friendship both hovv to knovve a perfect friend, and how to choose him. With a briefe treatise, or caueat, not to trust in worldly properitie. Translated out of Italian into English by Thomas Breme Gentleman.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07590</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17979.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110017</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845639</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845639</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10552</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07590)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10552)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 379:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mirrour of friendship both hovv to knovve a perfect friend, and how to choose him. With a briefe treatise, or caueat, not to trust in worldly properitie. Translated out of Italian into English by Thomas Breme Gentleman.</title>
                  <author>Breme, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>I. B., fl. 1584.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Abel Ieffes [and William Dickenson], dwelling in Sermon lane, neere Paules chayne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Original Italian source not traced.</note>
                  <note>Dickenson's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"An excellent aduertisement and councell to be by the readers well remembred: not to trust prosperous fortune, neither the felicities of this worldly life. .. Collected out of sundry tongues by I.B. [i.e. T.B.? i.e. Thomas Breme?]" has separate undated title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-C D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17979+ on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Friendship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fortune --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10552:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10552:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The mirrour of <hi>friendſhip:</hi> both hovv to knovve a Perfect friend, and how to chooſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a briefe treatiſe, or caueat, not to truſt in worldly proſperitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>Italian</hi> into <hi>Engliſh by Thomas Breme</hi> Gentleman.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Abel Ieſſes, dwelling in Sermon lane, neere Paules chayne. 1584.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10552:2"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of Thomas Kirton of Thorpe Mandeville</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10552:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the worſhipfull</hi> Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Thomas Kyrton eſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, chiefe common Sergeant of the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of London, A I. wiſheth increaſe of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proſperity, and after this life, that he may enioy the heauenly felicity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat is the force of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, (worſhipfull) which cauſeth thoſe that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with are beautified, ofte times to be praiſed, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and wondred at: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of ſuch as neuer ſawe them. Among which golden number (for there be not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch now liuing in this our iron age) I cannot but deſeruedly account your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: hauing heard you ſo notably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and well ſpoken of, not ſo much for your very good naturall inclination, as for your other extraordinary diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of vertue: and namely for your liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, curteſie, and affableneſſe towards all ſortes and degrees of people. Theſe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your honeſt and rare qualities: as your vpright dealinge and iuſte demeanure
<pb facs="tcp:10552:3"/>in ciuill affaires, are meanes that neuer faile to purchace fauour among the wel inclinans: and therefore being in you both ſo manifeſt and manifold, they cannot but giue grace among the wel diſpoſed. In conſideration whereof, I among the reſt (as one of the moſt that may doe leaſt) haue reuerenced your name, and often haue wiſhed ſome iuſte occaſion to befall me whereby I might finde the meanes to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that good will in open action towards your worſhippe, which along time in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete cogitation and thought I haue borne to ſo good a Gentleman. And now (in a happie time be it ſpoken) I haue taken opportunity, as conueniently it fell out, in ſignification of my foreſaid goodwyl which is far inferiour vnto my ſlender and weake abillity, to vndertake the preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of your worſhip with this ſmall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, being a mirrour, or looking glaſſe, wherein all are aduertiſed and taughte, not only what dueties of humanitie the moſt excellent name of friendſhippe doth mutually require; and would continually
<pb facs="tcp:10552:3"/>to be practiſed among men: but alſo what courſe a man is to keepe and take in the election and choyſe of a friend: Wherein ſuch as be wiſe will (no doubt) be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect: knowing that a faithfull and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward friend is to be reckoned one of the moſt precious ornaments and neceſſary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments belonging to this our variable life, and that without it (no more then the body of man without ſinewes and ioynts the ſocietie of men cannot conſiſt. Thus much in breuitie, touching the argument of this booke, by way of induction to the treatiſe it ſelfe: which becauſe it will ſufficiently commend it ſelfe to thoſe that be of iudgment able to diſcerne, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale whatſoeuer I might moſt iuſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in praiſe thereof. Beſeeching your worſhip, whome (among all other) the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons afore ſaid haue moued me to chooſe for the countenancing of the ſame, being (I muſt needes confeſſe) in reſpect of the valure vnworthy, but in conſideration of the vſe moſt worthy to be dedicated vnto your worſhip: perſwading my ſelfe, that
<pb facs="tcp:10552:4"/>you are none of thoſe that eſteeme the price of thinges by their outward barke, but by the inward pith: for the eie may faile in iudging, but the minde (if it be not diſtempered) doth ſildome miſſe. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this litile treatiſe therfore (I beſeech you) with fauour anſwerable to my good will, and as your leaſure ſhall ſerue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe nowe and then an houre or twaine in the reading therof: which if it pleaſe you to doe, I doubt not but you will like well of the labour: and beſides the honeſt recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which it affoordeth, applye what your iudgment maketh choiſe of, vnto your priuate vſe, And thus wiſhing proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to your worſhippe, acceptation to this my gifte, and a good opinion of the giuer. I conclude: hoping that mine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt wiſh ſhall not bee voyd of an happie iſſue and ſucceſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips, moſt humble to command, Abel leffes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:10552:4"/>
            <head>A Preface to the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, conſidering that in theſe dayes there is ſuch vnſteady friendſhip amongſt many, that it is hard to finde a perfect and true friend: for now friendly wordes are common, but when friendſhip commeth to the touch or proofe, the alteration is maruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: yea and ſometimes ſo daungerous that of friendes in wordes they will become enimies in deedes: for many that will be accounted as friendes, if a ſtorme of aduerfitie or a tempeſt of troubles fall out to thoſe they haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed friendſhip vnto, they vtterly withdrawe their good wils, and become ſo cold, that no regard is had at all of their former profeſſed good wils. I haue therfore in breife: diſcourſe ſhewed thee the true duetie of one friend to a nother: and partly howe to knowe, and choſe a good &amp; perfect friend, and alſo not to truſt in the proſperities of this world: which I deſire may be vnfainedly practiſed, and followed by thoſe that ſeeke to preferre vertuous, honeſt, and lawfull amitie. Thus I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to the diſcourſe, intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereof as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10552:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Abel Jeffe, incorporating the arms of the City of London and of the Worshipful Company of Stationers</figDesc>
                  <head>A I</head>
                  <q>PRAISE THE LORDE WITH HARPE AND SONGE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10552:5"/>
                  <head>A moſt excellent deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption vvhat one true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect friend ought to doe for another. Alſo how to chooſe ſuch a friend, with moſt perfect councells how to gouerne thy ſelfe in ſecuritie: both pleaſant to reade, and profitable to followe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He famous philoſopher <hi>Plato,</hi> being aſked by his ſcholers, why he went ſo often from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> into <hi>Sicilia,</hi> the way being long, and the ſea very tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous, and perillous to trauerſe and paſſe: he anſwered them: the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion that moues me to goe and come ſo often from <hi>Athens</hi> into <hi>Sicilia</hi> is for no other cauſe, but onely to ſee my friende Phocion, a man very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in his works and learning: wiſe in his ſayings, and iuſt and true in his wordes: and alſo for that he is my great friend, and enimie to vice, and a louer and follower of vertue, I goe
<pb facs="tcp:10552:6"/>willingly to ayde him to my power, and to conſult with him of all things that I know. And further he ſayd: you ought to knowe, my good ſchollers, that a good Philoſopher, or wiſe man, to viſite and ſuccour his friends, to practiſe and conferre with him, ought to eſtéeme the voiage little, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>: yea though he ſhould ſaile ouer the ſea, or ſhould iourney o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the land.
<note place="margin">Apollonius Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aneus a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher.</note> 
                     <hi>Appollonius Tianeus</hi> parted from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, paſſed through all Aſia, did ſaile ouer the great floud Nylus, 
<note place="margin">Nilus a famous Riuer in Egipt.</note> endured the coldes of the mount Caucaſus, 
<note place="margin">The mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine Caucaſus, a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine extreame colde.</note> &amp; ſuffered the great hoards of the Ryphean mountaines, 
<note place="margin">The Riphean mountaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame hoate.</note> paſſed the landes of the Maſſagets, entred into the great India, making this long peregrination &amp; trauel for no other reſpect, but to viſite and conferre with Hyarchos the Philoſophor, this great friend Ageſilaus, ſometime a famous Captaine among the Greekes, hauing knowledge that the king Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarius did hold priſoner another Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:10552:6"/>his very friend, leauing and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting apart al his affaires and trauels thorough infinite countries, till he came to the king, and after moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and reuerent ſalutation ſayd theſe wordes: I beſeech thee moſt renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned king, that it may pleaſe thée to pardon <hi>Mynotus,</hi> my ſingular friend, and thy humble ſubiect: and all that it ſhall pleaſe thee in fauour to doe for him, I ſhall and will account it done to myſelfe. And I aſſure thée, O king, thou canſt not chaſtice, or puniſh his perſon, but that thou ſhalt giue vnto me feeling of the lyke torment, that thou giueſt or cauſeſt to be done to him. The king Herode, after that <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> was vanquiſhed by the Emperor <hi>Auguſtus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Marcus Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius a noble Romaine and of great aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</note> he came to Rome, and ſet his crowne at the féete of Auguſtus;, and with a bolde hearte ſpake vnto him theſe words: thou ſhalt now know, O <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> if thou doeſt not already knowe it, that if <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> had rather
<pb facs="tcp:10552:7"/>beléeued me then his friend <hi>Cleopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cleopatra Queene of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt after the death of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Antonius, encloſed her ſelf in a tombe full of liue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, &amp; ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her life, for the great loue ſhee bare vnto Marcus Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius her louer.</note> thou ſhouldeſt haue prooued how great an enimie he had béene to thée. And thou ſhouldeſt likewiſe haue knowen, how great a friend I had béene to him, as yet I am: but he as a man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would rather gouerne himſelfe by the will of a woman, then be ledde by reaſon and wiſedome, he tooke of me mony, and of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> councell: and ſée here my Realme, my perſon and my Crowne here at thy féete, which I offer willingly to thée to diſpoſe at thy will and pleaſure: but with this conſideration, O inuincible <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> that no puniſhment or hurt be done, vpon my Lord and friend <hi>Marcus Antonius.</hi> For a true friend will not forſake his friend, not for the perill of death, nor after his death, be forgetfull or vnmindfull of him, although his perſon be abſent. By theſe examples and many other, that I could bring, it maybe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, what fayth and fidelytie one true
<pb facs="tcp:10552:7"/>friend oweth to an other, and what pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils one of them ought to aduenture for an other: for it is not ſufficient, that one friend be ſory for an other, for their miſhaps or euill fortunes, but to put them ſelues euen to the daunger of death, rather then to faile his friend in his extreame néed.</p>
                  <p>Hée then of good right ought to be called a friend, and eſteemed as true and perfect, that dothe willingly offer,
<note place="margin">¶ Note how to know a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect friend.</note> departe, and giue to his friend thoſe things that he lacketh, before he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his ayde: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpéedely commeth to ſuccor &amp; helpe his friend, béeing in peril, without calling, or ſending for. And therefore there is not, nor can not be in this world, better friendſhippe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this that I haue ſpoken of, which is that commeth with a frée heart of himſelfe to ayde his friend in neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to ſuccor him when he is in griefe or ſorrow: further we ought to know, that to continue and make per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect friendſhip, thou oughteſt not to
<pb facs="tcp:10552:8"/>enter into friendſhippe with many: following the counſell that <hi>Seneca</hi> the Philoſopher gaue to his friend <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillus,</hi> willing him to be the onely friend to one, and enimie to none: for the number of friends cauſeth greate importunity, the which cauſeth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect amity to diminiſh for conſidering well the liberty of our hearte, it is impoſſible, that one man ſhould, or can conforme or diſpoſe his nature and condition to the will and liking of many: nor that many ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues to the deſire and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of one. <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Saluſt</hi> were two Orators in Roome, very reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med amongſt the Romaines: which two Orators were mortall enimies: and during their enimities, <hi>Tully</hi> had for his friendes all the Senators in Roome, and <hi>Saluſt</hi> had no other friend in Roome but <hi>Marcus Antonius:</hi> and one day theſe two Orators, being in contention in wordes togither, <hi>Tully</hi> with great diſdaine did reproch
<pb facs="tcp:10552:8"/>
                     <hi>Saluſt,</hi> ſaying vnto him: what canſt thou doe, or enterpriſe in Roome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me? for wel thou knoweſt, that in all Roome thou haſt to thy friend but onely <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> and that I haue in Roome no enimie but him. <hi>Saluſt,</hi> made him a ready anſwere: thou makeſt great bragges, O <hi>Tully,</hi> for that thou haſt but one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie, mocking me, that I haue but one friend: but I hope in the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall gods, that all thy friends ſhall not be able to defend thée from deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that this one friend of mine if all be of power ſufficient to kéepe mée from daunger againſt thée and all thy adherents: and ſo it came to paſſe within fewe daies after, that <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> cauſed <hi>Tully</hi> to be ſlaine, and did aduance <hi>Saluſt</hi> to great auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority and honour. A friend may part to another body with all that he hath, as bread, wine, golde, ſiluer, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his temporal goods, but not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart: for that can not be parted nor giuen
<pb facs="tcp:10552:9"/>to more then one: for this is true and certaine: many hold it for great glory to haue many friendes, but if they conſider to what purpoſe: ſuch a number of friendes ſerue for no other cauſe, but to eate, drinke, walke, and talke together: not to ſuccor them in their neceſſities, with their goods, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and credits, nor brotherly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue them of their vices and faults, where in truth, where is a perfect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, neither my friend to me, nor I to my friend ought neuer to diſſemble but one to tell another their vices and faults:
<note place="margin">A perfect friend a great meaſure.</note> for in this world is not founds ſo great a treaſure that may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a true and perfect friend, conſidering that to a true and aſſured friend, a man may diſcouer the ſecrets of his hearte, and recounte to him all his griefes, truſt him with things touching his honour, and deliuer him to keep his goods and treaſures, which will ſucour vs, in our paines and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, councell vs in all perrilles
<pb facs="tcp:10552:9"/>and daungers, reioyce with vs in our proſperityes, and will be ſorrowfull with vs in our aduerſities, and diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of fortune. Finally, I conclude, that a faithfull friend doth neuer fayle to ayde vs during his life, nor to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine &amp; mourne for vs after our death. I agrée that gold and ſiluer is good, and parents and kinred, but farre better is true friends, without compariſon: for that all other things cannot helpe vs in our neceſſity, if by fortune it happen that we be plonged in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, but riches many times doth danger vs, yea &amp; doth further increaſe our perill, and deceiueth vs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vs to enterpriſe vnprofitable at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, leading vs to the toppes of craggy mountaynes, from which, we fall in great perrill, and perpetuall ruine: but a true friend ſéeing or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his friend in daunger or heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes doth miniſter to him of his goods, trauell and daunger his perſon, takes long and paynfull voiages, enters into
<pb facs="tcp:10552:10"/>debates and ſpeches, and doth hazard his perſon, onely to helpe and releaſe his friend out of perill, with ſuche a pure affection &amp; amitie, that he would yet doe more for him if it were in his power: hauing then preſuppoſed that it is neceſſary to chooſe a friend, &amp; only to vſe him alone, great conſideration is to be had in the choyce and election of ſuch a one, leaſt thou finde thy ſelfe deceiued in thy truſt, in vttering thy ſecretes to him:
<note place="margin">How to choſe a perfect friend.</note> haue regarde that he be not couetous, vnpacient, or angry: a great talker, ſeditious, or a mouer of ſtrife, neither preſumptuous: for if he be infected with theſe vices, thou wert better to haue him thine enimie, then to chooſe him for thy friend: but thy perfect friend ought to be of good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and honeſt cuſtomes: that is to be gentle of nature, wiſe in his purpoſes, and paynefull in trauels, patient in iniuries, ſober in eating and drinking good in councell giuing: and aboue all faythfull and conſtant
<pb facs="tcp:10552:10"/>in amity, and kéeping thy ſecretes: and ſuch a one thou maiſt ſurely chooſe for thy friend. And where want and defaylance ſhalbe of theſe conditions, to flye his friendſhip as a daungerous peſtilence. Holde this for a certayne thing, that much worſe is the amity of a fayned friend and fantaſticall, then the malice of an open enimie. We ſe none will buie a horſe, till firſt he hath ſéene him goe, and wel vewed him: ſilke nor cloath without ſéeing and féeling it: wine without taſting it: fleſhe without cheapening it: nor houſe without vewing it within: nor inſtruments without hearing them ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, and played vppon: by a more great reaſon thou oughteſt in chooſing thy friend, to know his behauiour and wiſdome and vertues, long before thou admitteſt him as thy ſecrete friend.
<note place="margin">Note the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus order in friendſhip.</note> The Emperor <hi>Auguſtus</hi> was warie &amp; difficil in admitting a ſpecial friend, but after he had receiued him into his friendſhip, he would neuer leaue
<pb facs="tcp:10552:11"/>him, nor reiecte him for any cauſe or diſpleaſure. Friendſhippe ought to bée exerciſed with good men, &amp; in vertuous actions: for although a man make his friend Lord of his ſecretes, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet alwayes reaſon ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vertue frée. <hi>Plutarke</hi> ſaieth in his Politicks, that we were much better, to ſell dearely to our friends our good turnes,
<note place="margin">Note Plutarks opinion.</note> and friendſhippes, either in proſperity or aduerſitie, then to féeds them with faire &amp; diſſembling words, &amp; vaine promiſes, not meaning to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme any of our friendſhips offered. I wiſh theſe my trauells might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to them, that ſhall peruſe that I haue written of Amity, and choiſe of a friend, hauing writte fréely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out flattery. <hi>Saluite</hi> in his booke of the Iugurthine warres, ſhews that it is no leſſe commendation for a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to write truly the valiant acts of the worthy, then to the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to haue executed his charge with valure and worthineſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:10552:11"/>armes: for often it happeneth, the captaine to be ſlaine in gaining the battaile and victory, yet faileth he not to be reuiued by good reputation,
<note place="margin">Good fame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth after death,</note> that he gained before his death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet downe in true hiſtory by the writer. Good counſell is of great effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie in a friend:
<note place="margin">Marcus Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius a famous empeour of Rome.</note> as ſaid <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> to his ſecretary <hi>Panuci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> ſaying that a man with money may ſatiſfie and recompence many pleaſures and good turnes done him, but to reward good counſell all the goods had néede to ſatiſfie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence. If we will beléeue aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent hiſtoryes, we ſhall finde it true, that the vertuous Emperors, fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Kings, and hardy Captaines, going to the warres, to conquere their enimies, haue alwaies bene deſirous to haue in their company ſome diſcréete and learned philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, as well to counſell with, as alſo to recorde in writing their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures and noble faets. Great <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10552:12"/>had <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> King <hi>Gyrus, Chilon:</hi> King <hi>Ptholome, Pithimon:</hi> King <hi>Pirrhus Zatvru:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The notable emperors and kinges haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> the emperour <hi>Auguſt Simonides Scipio, Sophocles:</hi> the emperour <hi>Traian, Plutarke:</hi> the emperour <hi>Antonius p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> Georgias.</hi> The company of al theſe philoſophers and excellent men of the worlde ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued only for good counſell, wherein their ſervices deſerued praiſe: as did the valiant Captaines, by their hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; manhood. The emperour <hi>Nero</hi> aſked <hi>Seneca</hi> the philoſopher, what he thought of <hi>Scipio</hi> the Affrican and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a to the Cenſor: he anſwered the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour that it was:
<note place="margin">As Armes is neceſſarie ſo is learning alſo.</note> as neceſſary that <hi>Cato</hi> ſhould be borne into the worlde, for the common wealth, as Scipio to, for the warres: for as much, as the good <hi>Cato,</hi> by his counſell did: chace the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out of the common wealthe: and Scipio by his actiuity and valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in armes, did chaſtice the enimy of the common wealth. And ſurely who ſhall followe the counſell here
<pb facs="tcp:10552:12"/>written, ſhal finde them neceſſary and profitable: and ſhal help him to aſſure his eſtate. For all the troupe of philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers do affirme, that the felicitie doth not conſiſt in great puiſſance, nor in hauing worldly riches,
<note place="margin">To deſerue wel is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of good men.</note> but in deſeruing wel. For the honour, fauor, and greatneſſe of this mortall life is of more practiſe in them that deſerue it then to them that poſſeſſe it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſerte, by happe or fortune: for if the earthquakes doo moſt hurte where be the moſt coſtly buildinges, and the tempeſt and lightning is moſt extreeme vpon the high mountaines, more then in the vallies, and low pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and that in the greateſt and moſt proud and moſt peopled cities, the peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilence doth moſt rage, more then in other places of ſmal inhabitation: and the birds be entrapped in the nets vnknowen to them: and the calmneſſe of the Sea is token of ſome great tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt to come: and that after long health ſickneſſe is moſt daungerous: ſo doe
<pb facs="tcp:10552:13"/>I inferre hereby, that it is neceſſary for al men to beware of fained friends and beware of falling into ruine and daunger of euil fortune, &amp; entrapping of diſſembled friendes. The emperor <hi>Auguſtus</hi> aſked <hi>Virgil</hi> how he might long maintaine himſelfe in his empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; be liked of the common weale: he anſwered, often to examine thy ſelf, O Emperour, and to know that as thou excelleſt all in eſtate and degrée, and authority, ſo oughteſt thou to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe all other in vertus and noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: which was a moſt excellent and wiſe anſwere. The ancient and wiſe Hiſtoriographers did praiſe greatly the greatneſſe of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Ptholome,</hi> the inſtice of <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> the clemency of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> the patience of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> the veritis of <hi>Traian,</hi> the pittie of <hi>Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> the temperance of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> the continency of <hi>Scipio,</hi> and the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Theodoſius:</hi> ſo that theſe great princes got their great reputation
<pb facs="tcp:10552:13"/>more by their vertues, then valiancy and great déedes of armes, victories, &amp; tryumphes. One thing is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that how vicious, diſſolute or diſſembling a man be, when he conſidereth, and remembreth his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doings, and thinkes what he hath béene, what he he is,
<note place="margin">It is a wicked thing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble.</note> and what may happen to him, for diſſembling with his friends, and other his euill doings, that if any ſparke of grace, or any goodneſſe remaine in him, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent him of his former euil, &amp; it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth heauineſſe to him, when he hath done wickedly: for ſo ſay truly, we neuer receyue ſo much pleaſure and contentment in doing euill, as we ſhall finde diſpleaſure, griefe, venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and puniſhment, after euil doing. Certaine counſells and good aduertiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I will giue all men,
<note place="margin">Note theſe councels.</note> neuer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer nor declare to any perſon all that thou thinkeſt, nether make any priuy how much treaſure, or valure in goods thou haſte: for if thou canſt not
<pb facs="tcp:10552:14"/>haue all thou deſireſt, doe not ſay all thou knoweſte, nether doe hurte, to any that thou maieſt, and is in thy power to doe: for commonly greate hurte doeth a man procure to himſelfe in following his owne will, without reſting vpon the rocke of good conſideration and reaſon. The ſecond is to be wary, &amp; carefull, neuer to put to the hazzard of variant fortune thoſe things that concerne thy perſon, thy eſtate and goods: for the wiſe will neuer repoſe or put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in perrill vppon hope, where daunger and perrill is likely to enſue: neither thinke, that all ſeruices and proffers that ſhalbe made them in words and friendly proteſtations ſhal be performed for commonly thoſe: that moſt liberally offer their friendſhips, are ſlack in performing, ye a ſometime redyeſt, if they ſée a man hath néede of him, or that fortune frowne vpon him to whome he profeſſeth great good wil, none ſhall be found a greater enimie
<pb facs="tcp:10552:14"/>then he: neuer be thou a medler in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens buſineſſe, or matters that touth thée not, neither be ſlacke in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thyne owne: for a time loſt in doing thy buſineſſe, the like oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye thou ſhalt neuer finde, or recouer againe: if thou ſtand in daunger, and that there be hope of helpe,
<note place="margin">the duties of a perfect friend.</note> ſpéedily preuent thy miſhappe, leaſt by detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the time all hope of helpe may faile thée: chooſe them for thy friends aſſured and faithfull, that will haue care of thée, &amp; hold thée vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falling, &amp; not them,
<note place="margin">do not opreſſe or hurte the poore.</note> that after thou art fallen will proffer thée their hand to helpe thée vp againe: hurt not thoſe that thou haſt power to hurt: for the cryes and curſſes of the poore, and ſometimes of other, being wronged commeth before the preſence of God, demaunding iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and vengeance: in that thou art of abilitie to do good, help thy friends: parentes and kindred, and alſo the poore. In counſell that that thou ſhalt giue, be not affectionate: be not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous,
<pb facs="tcp:10552:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10552:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10552:16"/>or ſeuere againſt them you may commaund: nether doe any thinge without good conſideration: kéepe company with them that will ſpeake the trueth, and flée from them that be lyars, flatterers, and diſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: for more account is to be made of them, that will forewarne thée of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill that may follow to thée, then to thoſe that will giue counſell after thou haſt receyued the hurte: For a wiſe man is to thinke that although euils commonly happen not to the prouident man, yet to thinke poſſible they may come, is wiſdome: for it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth, the ſhippe ſoddainely by tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt to wracke, when the Sea is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before very calme &amp; quiet,
<note place="margin">A wiſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</note> and the more fauourable thou findeſt fortune, ſo much the more haue thou feare that ſhe will be cruell, and deſpitefull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the: make no ſmall accounte of this little worke, and briefe aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſment, for experience teacheth vs, that a little diamond is of more eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb facs="tcp:10552:16"/>then a great ballays. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider alſo, how the time flyeth away, and all things come to an ende:
<note place="margin">A notable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</note> and that thou muſt depart from thy riches, be forſaken of friendes, and thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to dye, and thoſe that ſhould ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede and follow thée ſhall vtterly forget thée: and thou ſhalt not knowe, to whome thy goods and ſucceſſion, ſhall come, and leſſe how thy children and heires ſhall gouerne themſelues, nor whether they ſhould proue good and vertuous, or not. <hi>Chilon</hi> the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, being aſked what thing he did finde in this worlde vpon which fortune had no power, he anſwered: there be two thinges onely in this worlde, which time cannot conſume,
<note place="margin">Fame and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will neuer be couered.</note> nor fortune deſtroy, that is fame and good reputation of a man, that is written in bookes, and veritie hidde, for that veritye and trueth may be hidde and clowded for a time, but in the ende it will manifeſte it ſelfe: if thou wilt ſometime, for the recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:10552:17"/>and contentment of thy ſpirites. To peruſe theſe councels, here ſette downe, thou ſhalt haue cauſe to think it a good trauaile, and woorke and time beſtowed well. As <hi>Suetonius Tranquillus</hi> doth write of <hi>Iulius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Time ſpente vertuouſly.</note> that among all the warres and continuall following them, he did not ceaſſe to reade and write ſome thing, yea being in the campe, and in his tente, commonly in one hande he held his ſpeare, and in the other his penne, to write his commentaries. Man is to make great accounte of the time loſte, more then to haue care to kéepe his treaſures and riches: for the time being well emploied ſhall bring him to ſaluation, and treaſures euill gotten ſhall be the cauſe of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation, ouer and beſides a great trauaile and wearyneſſe to the body of man, and greater perrill to his ſoule, when he occupies all his dayes and all his life in the affaires, of this world, and cannot ſeparate
<pb facs="tcp:10552:17"/>his mind from theſe worldly affaires, till he be called to the place, where he muſt make accounte of all his wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched doings, and leaue his body in the earth, a foode for woormes. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, I aſſure you all that ſhall reade this ſhorte aduertiſemente and councell; that of all the treaſures, rit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, proſperities, ſeruices, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers that you haue, and poſſeſſe in this your mortal life, you ſhall carrie nothing with you, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the time that you haue well em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and ſpente vertuouſly, during the courſe, and time of this your mortall life.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10552:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10552:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An excellent aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and councell to be by the readers well remembred: not to truſt proſperous fortune, neither the felicities of this worldly life. With diuers hiſtories, and antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties approouing the ſame by examples.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Collected out of ſundry tongues by. I. B.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AT LONDON Printed for Abell Ieffes, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Sermon lane neere Paules chaine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10552:19"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10552:19"/>
                  <head>A godly aduertiſement to the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>mong al the Romains, the great <hi>Cato</hi> the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor was had in ſingular reputation, which in all the progreſſe of his life was ſo honeſt, and in gouernement of the common wealth was ſo right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a Iuſticiar, that by good righte there was written vpon the Gate of of his houſe theſe Epitaphes: O moſt fortunate <hi>Cato,</hi> the reputation of whome is ſuch toward the common wealth, that there cannot be found a man that is able to Iuſtifie that euer he ſawe thée doe euill, or that any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer durſte pray thée of any fauour or grace in any cauſe that was not iuſt and honeſt.
<note place="margin">Cato would haue no ſtatue or Image of him ſelf ſet vp as the notable Romans vſed.</note> And by good reaſon ſuch honour was done hym: for amonge all the noble and famous Romaynes, it was he alone that would not ſuffer that any Image of himſelfe ſhould be erected or ſet vp in the capytoll of
<pb facs="tcp:10552:20"/>Rome, as the other famous Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes did vſe for their honour and remembrance to continue. Many ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing great maruell why this worthy <hi>Cato</hi> refuſed the honour, where vpon were great diſcourſes and ſpéeches in Rome: <hi>Cato</hi> vpon a day being in the Senate houſe, ſayd openlie vnto them: the cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wil not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſnent to erect my Image in the capitoll, is for that I deſire that after death my good workes ſhould rather be followed,
<note place="margin">A mans good works rather to be followed then his image to be looked vpon.</note> then to goe after, &amp; beholde my I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and enquire what houſe or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents I came of, and what euill I haue done in my life time: and ſo my euill deſerts might cauſe my ſtatue or Image to be throwen downe, to my infamy and diſhonour after my death: for it happeneth often that thoſe which by variant fortune, from bace eſtate be mounted to great honour, come afterwards by the ſame occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be plonged and ouer throwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into vtter ruine and defamy: for many be
<pb facs="tcp:10552:20"/>reuerenced and honoured for their great riches, while they poſſeſſe them, which after are mocked when fortune hath abaced them, and depriued them of their riches. <hi>Lucian</hi> doth recite that Pompey the great was wonte to ſay:
<note place="margin">Note Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peius wordes of the varietie of Fortune.</note> my friends we haue little cauſe to truſt the flatterings of fortune: as for my parte, I haue prooued by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that obtayned the rule of the Roman empire before I did once pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, or had any hope to doe it, &amp; you know how ſodainly againe it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from me, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I nothing ſuſpected any ſuch hap to come. <hi>Lucius Seneca</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing baniſhed from Rome, wrot a letter to his mother <hi>Albine,</hi> in which, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting her he ſaid theſe words: know this for certaine, good mother <hi>Albine,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in my life I neuer gaue credit to, or truſted fortune,
<note place="margin">The wiſe will not preſume vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good hap.</note> although there were betwéene me and her many ſhowes of friendlineſſe: but what ſo euer ſhe as a traitres conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to, whereby I found my ſelfe in reſt and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity:
<pb facs="tcp:10552:21"/>it was not done by fortune, by will to ceaſe to hurt me, but onely to giue me the more great fall, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimuled aſſurance of her furious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge towards me: yea euen with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furies, that one campe of them come after another armd againſt me to giue battayle: for all that ſhe giues me, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ryches or honour by her libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, I accept it but lent, &amp; not to continue, but ſmall time: the promiſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fortune offers me, the honours ſhe doth mée, and the riches ſhe giues me, I lay it by accompte in my houſe by it ſelfe, that alwayes I looke to loſe it euery howre of the day and night: euen when it pleaſeth her to take all againe, without any thing troubling my minde or ſpirites, or making do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous or heauy my heart any thing at all, and further knowe, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I haue bene beholding to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, yet I haue alwayes deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined neuer to put truſt in any thing ſhe giues me, nor hope in my hearte
<pb facs="tcp:10552:21"/>ſafely to kéepe it, otherwiſe then for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time to take pleaſure in it, but no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance. I loue to haue fortune my friend, rather then mine enimie, but notwithſtanding, if I loſe all that ſhe giues mée, it ſhall grieue mée no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: therefore I conclude finally that when fortune cauſeth or ſuffereth my houſe to be robbed and aſſayled by the greateſt extremity ſhée can: yet ſhall it not cauſe me to giue one ſigh from my heart. We reade that King <hi>Phillip</hi> the father of great King <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A wiſe kinge that doubted proſperous for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</note> when he had receiued newes of thrée victories that his Captaines and men of warre had gotten in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places, he immediatly knéeled down, ioyning his hands togither, lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp his eies to the heauens, &amp; ſpake theſe wordes: O cruell fortune: Oh moſt pittifull gods: after my proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſe, I moſt humbly pray you that after ſuch great glory as you haue giuen mée at this preſent, you will moderate the chaſtiſement, I
<pb facs="tcp:10552:22"/>feare will follow:
<note place="margin">How fearefull the king Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip was.</note> and that it may be with ſuch pitty, that it be not the cauſe of my extreame ruine and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for I am certaine that after great fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity and proſperity of this life there followeth great miſfortunes and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces. All theſe examples afore reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted be worthy to be noted and often called to our remembraunce, that by thinking on them we may know how little we haue to truſt in fortune, and how much we haue to feare the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring fawning and felicityes of this life. True it is that we be very frayle by nature, &amp; therefore fall into many fragilities dayly. This world as a traytor doth vſe alwayes to giue vs troubles and ſorrowes, as a recharge after our good happes. So that we may by good right call our felicities cawteries or burning diſeaſes in the fleſh almoſt incurable to heale: for that the world is ſuttle to finde euery fraud and miſchéefe, without giuing vs warning to foreſée the ſequell that
<pb facs="tcp:10552:22"/>followes. As is manifeſtly ſéene: for we fall into a number of miſhappes before we can beware.
<note place="margin">After pleaſure payne follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> Yea if it fortune that ſometimes we happen vpon pleaſures, or contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of mind, by good fortune, as we terme it, there followes a daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous gulfe of troubles, and a ſea of dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thoughts: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we hoping, as right worldlings, to holde in certenty our good happes, riches &amp; treaſures of this world, are ſuddaynly entrapped and toyled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nets of miſfortune, hidden vnder a vaine hope of our good fortunes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing with vs. As though we had good fortune taken in our netts, and ſo forced to abide with vs: as had one notable Captaine <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> (as poets fayne) for that hée was happy in all his enterpriſes, wherefore,
<note place="margin">Timotheus a fortunate Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne.</note> how high, great, riche, or how wiſe ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we accompt our ſelues: of this wée may be ſure and certaine, that all men that be in the world, ſhall find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues deceiued in following the world, and the practiſes vſed in the ſame. And ſuch is our folly that after a little good fortune our wittes be captiuated and drowned in our
<pb facs="tcp:10552:23"/>owne conceite, that we offer our ſelues as a prayr to euill haps and froward for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune moſt commonly irrecuperable. O trayterous world, which for a ſhort time doeſt flatter vs, and ſodainely with the twinckling of an eye doeſt hunt vs from thée: ſodaynly thou giueſt vs occaſion to be merry,
<note place="margin">trayterous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orlde.</note> and by and by makeſt vs hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy and ſad: now thou doeſt aduaunce vs, and ſhortly after abace vs, &amp; inchant vs: vnder the guiſe of troubles doth ſo tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and weary vs, and makeſt vs ſo faſt in thy toyles &amp; troublous laborinthes, that we can not eſcape thy engines, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, the more knowing a man hawty and glorius, the more doth prouide for him honors and riches, deinty fare, bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull women &amp; other worldly pleaſures and reſtes, which is to no other end, but after all theſe wiſhed pleaſures and dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines miniſtered vnto vs, euen as a baite is to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fiſhes we are ſodainly &amp; more eaſily taken in the nettes &amp; ſnares of our owne wickednes: but as for our firſt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations that by the world be preſented vnto vs, wée thinke it vnpoſſible that we ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:10552:23"/>be ſo often aſſayled with aduerſe fortune, and our power y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſmal to reſiſt, is cauſe to vs of great hardyneſſe: but I would haue one that is moſt affectionate to the world, or loueth it moſt, ſhould tell me, what hope or recompence he or they can recouer after they be deceiued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world and their truſt they haue of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their brittle pleaſures: by truſting whereof they after endure ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brances of fortune. If we ſhould euer hope they would continue with vs, that were a great folly and mockery,
<note place="margin">Death mo neare whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lif is moſt deſire</note> conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the time when our life is moſte ſwéete and agréeable to vs, then is death moſt neare vs, euen moſte ſodainly to intrap vs: for when we thinke to haue peace and truce with fortune, at the ſame inſtant ſhe rayſes a camp, and ſtirs vp a new war againſt vs. And I certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue that which I haue written and ſayd ſhalbe red of many, and remembred and beléeued of few: that is, that I haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen great dolors and lamentations to haue bene in the houſes of many, where before hath bene great ioye, laughing and
<pb facs="tcp:10552:24"/>reioycing in this world, which is a giuer of euill,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he world deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ibed.</note> a ruine of good things, a heape of wickednes, a tirant of vertue, an enimy of peace, a friend of wars, a mayntayner of errors, a riuer of vices, a perſecutor of vertues, an inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter of nouelties, a graue of ignorance, a forreſt of miſchefe, a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deſire of the fleſhly delightes &amp; inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable delicacy, in féeding &amp; gourmandiſe, and finally, a <hi>Charibdis</hi> or moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous gulfe, in which doth periſh many noble harts, and a very <hi>Scilla,</hi> where alſo doth periſh al our deſires &amp; good thoughts for the people doe not accompt them hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py that deſerue well,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Peoples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ccompt.</note> but thoſe that poſſes the riches and treaſures, which vpon the ſuddaine ſome times they ſée fortune vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſpoyle them of that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſeſſe: but of that minde were not the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers &amp; Sages, neither at this day thoſe that be wiſe and vertuous, we ſée ſome loſe their riches and ſome their liues and treaſures togither that haue bene long in gathering &amp; getting: for where is greate riches enuy followeth, as the ſhadow the body. <hi>Ewſenides</hi> was in great fauour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10552:24"/>King <hi>Ptholome</hi> of Egipt, &amp; thereby very rich:
<note place="margin">Note this.</note> reioycing in this proſperity of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, ſaid to another his great familiar: the king can giue me no more then the rule of all that he hath: his friend anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him: yet aduerſe fortune may take it all from thée, &amp; then it will be a gréeuous day to thée, to deſcend the degrées of good hap,
<note place="margin">The cruelty of a king in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</note> ſhortly after it followed that king <hi>Ptholome</hi> found <hi>Ewſenides</hi> talking ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly with a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that king <hi>Ptholome</hi> loued greatly, wherefore the king taking high diſpleaſure againſte them both, commaunded the woman to drink poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and cauſed the man to be hanged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his gate. <hi>Plaucian</hi> was ſo greatly eſtéemed of the Emperor <hi>Seuerus,</hi> that al that <hi>Plaucian</hi> preferred, the Emperour thought well of,
<note place="margin">Plaucian ſlayn by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours ſonne.</note> &amp; willingly accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his requeſts: yet was he ſodainly ſlain in the kings chamber by the hands of <hi>Baſian</hi> the Emperours eldeſt ſonne. the Emperour <hi>Commodus,</hi> ſonne of the good Emperour <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> loued one ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that he had, called <hi>Cleander,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The ende of extreame co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe.</note> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very wiſe &amp; olde, but yet couetous: which
<pb facs="tcp:10552:25"/>man being aſked pay by the ſouldiers of Rome, ſhewing the emperours warrant vnder his hand,
<note place="margin">Princes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements are dangerous to be broken.</note> yet would not <hi>Cleander</hi> make pay wherefore the Emperour ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his diſobedience, &amp; the ſmall reſpect he had to doe the emperours commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, commaunded imediatly that <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> ſhould be put to a ſhameful death, and all his goodes confiſcate, <hi>Alcimeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> a famous king in Gréece, had one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſerued him, named <hi>Pannonian,</hi> one that the king held in ſingular fauour and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, in ſo much that the king plaied at tennis with this his ſeruant: in playing, a contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grew betwéene them, where the chace was marked,
<note place="margin">It is daunger to contend with princes.</note> the king ſaid in one place, <hi>Pannonion</hi> in another, the king being in a great fury, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his garde to take him, &amp; in the ſame place that <hi>Pannonian</hi> affirmed the chace to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king cauſed <hi>Panonians</hi> head to be cut of, the Emperour <hi>Conſtance</hi> fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red greatly one <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> in ſo much that all matters in the common wealth, the wars, and houſhould affaires were done by <hi>Hortenſius</hi> his direction: the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour
<pb facs="tcp:10552:25"/>hauing cauſe to ſigne letters very haſtely, &amp; <hi>Hortenſlus</hi> brought the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour a pen that was euill made, or elſe ſome faulte in the ynke, that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour could not readily write with it, the Emperour being very angry cauſed <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſius</hi> head to be cut of w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out any ſtay.
<note place="margin">A cruel puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for a light fault.</note> Many other examples might here be brought in. How great <hi>Alexander</hi> ſlew in his anger <hi>Craterus.</hi> King <hi>Pirrhus</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſcretary Alphabot to be ſlain. The emperour <hi>Bittalio, Cincinatus</hi> his deare friend. <hi>Domician,</hi> his chamberlen <hi>Rufus,</hi> by which examples may be ſeene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the alteration of proſpetity and riches, &amp; for light occaſions alſo death. King <hi>Demetrius</hi> aſked the Philoſopher <hi>Euripides,</hi> what he thought of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man &amp; of the vncertainty of this life, he anſwered: O king, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing certaine in this life, but that ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine eclipſes and incumberances chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth. King <hi>Demetrius</hi> anſwered: you might well ſay they change daily, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt from houre to houre. So that there may be inferred by the words of this
<pb facs="tcp:10552:26"/>good king, that changes of perrill &amp; daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger come in the twinkling of an eye, but to ſay the truth, the man that would liue content,
<note place="margin">Many miſhaps might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> and foreſée theſe euill happes, might well auoid moſt miſchances: but aboundance &amp; proſperity of fortime doth ſo blind vs, that coueting ſtill to inrich our ſelues, and to commaund, brings vs in the end to infelicity and torments of the minde. Finally I conclude, that all men ought to liue ſagely and wiſely, to foreſée the directions of their liues and dayly affayres. For moſt true it is that none liue in any proſperous eſtate that hath no enimies, noting their doings: wherefore let all men direct a vertuous courſe in their liuing in this worlde, by meanes whereof their owne quietneſſe may followe in their life time, and be a good example for their poſterity to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, after their deathes.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by Abel Ieffes and William Dickenſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10552:26"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
